<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief resolution of the present case of the subjects of Scotland in order to Episcopal government, by sacred authority re-established in this kingdome. Or, Episcopus Scoticanus redivivus. For the satisfaction of the people. Authore Phil-Alethio.</title>
            <author>Phil-Alethio.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223956</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135127</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135127)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2473:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief resolution of the present case of the subjects of Scotland in order to Episcopal government, by sacred authority re-established in this kingdome. Or, Episcopus Scoticanus redivivus. For the satisfaction of the people. Authore Phil-Alethio.</title>
                  <author>Phil-Alethio.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Episcopal Church in Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135127:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135127:1"/> A BRIEF RESOLUTION Of the preſent Caſe of the SUBJECTS OF SCOTLAND, In order to Epiſcopal Government, by Sacred Authority re-eſtabliſhed in this KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>Epiſcopus Scoticanus Redivivus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſatisfaction of the People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THORE PHIL-ALETHIO.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſ. 10. 4.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>They have ſpoken words, ſwearing falſely, in making a Covenant; thus judgement ſpringeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field.</hi>
               </p> 
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Numb. 30. 5, 8, 12, 13, 15, 16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the husband or father, ſhall any wiſe diſallow of the vows or oaths, of his wife or daughter, after that he hath heard them; they do become void, and neither ſtand nor bind; and the Lord ſhall forgive her, becauſe the husband or father diſallowed her.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="resolution">
            <pb facs="tcp:135127:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135127:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEF RESOLUTION Of the preſent Caſe of the SUBJECTS OF SCOTLAND, In order to Epiſcopal Government, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed by Sacred Authority in this KINGDOME.</head>
            <p>CASE. <hi>Whether the Lieges of</hi> Scotland, <hi>have any real neceſſity impoſed on them by any Oath or Covenant, to any juſt ſcrupling of cloſing with Epiſcopacy, to which by Sacred Authority this Kingdom is lately reſtored.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith what Caution and Warineſſe men ought to imbarque themſelves in all manner of Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, needs not much Oil or Labour ſpent upon the Enquiry; Scripture alone is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently able to inſtruct us, ſometimes terming it a bond, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20 37. Sometimes a ſnare,
<hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 2. And verily he who doth unadviſedly engage, doth many a time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle himſelf in an intrigue of inextricable difficulties, out of which, he cannot ſo eaſily winde himſelf; eſpecially in the matter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135127:3"/> of Oaths in the time of popular confuſions; Men then being
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to ſo many precipices of danger, in making Ship-wrack of Conſcience, through Errour and Miſ-priſion, on the one hand; with fear and force, on the other. We need not much Range abroad in the inqueſt, after witneſſes to this truth, our own home-bred late popular Covenants and Engagements, bearing ſo much lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table evidence of it upon them, to this very day; whileas theſe are ſtill made uſe of, as the Maſter-engines of ſome Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick-Male-contents, for ſtaving of, honeſt and well-meaning People, from that duty, they owe to God, their Mother-Church, and our Gracious and undoubted Soveraign, by making it their conſtant and zealous endeavour to invegle the people, by preſenting theſe as indiſpenſable Bonds, which are, indeed, but ſo many ſnares, and ſo many Flaxen Fetters and Cob-webs, which themſelves in the moſt eſſential Points, do break through at pleaſure, (as God-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhall be made clearly to appear, in the ſequel of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) and yet amuſe the Vulgar, who reach not to the depths of things, as if theſe were inviolable and indiſſoluble ſacred wyths, wherein they muſt ly tied neck and heel.</p>
            <p>That therefore, we may make appear, how far, the late Oaths, Covenants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby the people of this Land did engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, againſt Epiſcopal Government, in this Church, do bind, and how far they may be diſpenſed with, as to an after-performance, and ſo whether to be reckoned among Sacred Bonds, or ſinful Snares: I ſhall (howbeit aſmuch hath been already ſaid, to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſinfulneſſe and invalidity of theſe Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by His late Majeſty of Immortal Memory, in His Admirable Book, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by the Learned &amp; Renowned Doctors of
<hi>Aberdene,</hi> in their Demands &amp; Duplys, as may put to ſilence all thoſe who, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their duty, have not forfaulted a Sober, Rational mind) lay down very briefly, ſome few irrefragable Propoſitions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bindingneſſe of Oaths and Covenants in the general; from which, I ſhall draw a reſolution of the Caſe in hand, by way of Corrolary; and then leave it, upon the ſober, and impartial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, of all un-prejudged, to reſolve, whether theſe Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Engagements be the indiſpenſable Oaths of God, (as ſome
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o uſually phraſe it, for amuſing the ſimple) or not. As for theſe P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nciples and Propoſitions, which, (I truſt) may infer a full and ſatisfactory ſolution of the preſent Caſe; I ſhall, ſtudying brevity, reduce them all to theſe eight, following.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:135127:3"/> 
               <hi>Propoſ. jma.</hi> There is this firſt Propoſition. No man may ſwear, or by ſubtilty or violence induce others to ſwear, unlawfully. This is full of evidence; none being free to ſin, or any-wiſe to engage others to ſin; but to ſwear, or to induce another by any means, to ſwear unlawfully, is, beyond all peradventure ſinful; and therefore. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but we leave this on its own evidence, and goe to the next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſ. 2da.</hi> There is this ſecond Propoſition. That is not a lawfull or juſtifiable Oath, which is not attended with Truth, Righteouſneſſe and Judgement. This Propoſition is borrowed, from the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, Jer. 4. 2. Thou ſhalt ſwear, the Lord liveth, in truth, in righteouſneſſe, and in judgement.</hi> Where we find the Holy Ghoſt, laying down three grand qualifications of a lawful Oath; <hi>viz.</hi>
1. That it be in truth; which requireth not only, that the thing ſworn be true, but alſo, candor and ſincerity, in the undertaking, without all falſehood and double-mindedneſſe. 2. That it be in righteouſneſſe; which requireth, that the thing ſworn, be juſt, and in it ſelf lawful to be undertaken: which is all one with that which Judicious Caſuiſts ſpeak,
<hi>viz.</hi> That the Oath be undertaken, <hi>Super re licitâ;</hi> Since God is not to be aſſum'd, either for Witneſſe or Over-ſeer of a thing ſimply unjuſt (as, if the matter ſworn be unlawful, he is) who is a God of moſt pure eyes, and cannot behold iniquity: And moreover, becauſe it binds a man, to the doing of a thing, which yet the very intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal condition of the matter, refuſeth a performance of. Upon this ground,
<hi>Herod</hi> was not bound, notwithſtanding his promiſe and oath, to deliver the <hi>Baptiſt's</hi> head, to <hi>Herodias</hi> her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; no more, were theſe fourty Conſpirators againſt St. <hi>Paul, Act. 23. 12,
13, &amp;c.</hi> Neither, <hi>David</hi> by his having ſworn and vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the deſtruction of churliſh <hi>Nabal, 1 Sam. 25. 22, &amp;c.</hi> And then 3. that it be in judgement. Which requireth, that the thing undertaken by Oath, be not unmeet and undue to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but due and convenient, and, which is moſtly imported, that it be deliberately and penſiculately ſet about. Theſe three qualifications, are ingredients abſolutely neceſſary, for conſtituting a lawful Oath; being, that it is intrinſecally ſinful, to ſwear ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſly, or unjuſtly, or to ſwear the performance of that, which is unmeet and inconvenient to be undertaken, as alſo, to engage raſhly, unadviſedly, and without deliberation into any Covenant or Oath whatſomever. But,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:135127:4"/> 
               <hi>Propoſ. 3ia.</hi> There is this third Propoſition. A promiſſary Oath, which is undertaken, to the certain prejudice of another mans juſt right, cannot be attended with juſtice. This needs not much debate upon its evidence; being, that <hi>Juſtitia tribuit
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uique ſnum,</hi> Juſtice being a vertue, whereby, to every man his Due, and Own are rendered: If therefore any Oath engage, to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that which doth clearly prejudge any other, in that which is his due and juſt right, it is an unrighteous Oath, and becauſe of its injuſtice, is, of it ſelf, vacated from being binding or obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſ. 4ta.</hi> There is this fourth Propoſition. No prejudice or violence, done to the right of any other man, can be ſo highly dangerous and ſinful, as that prejudice and violence which are done to the juſt right of the Supream Magiſtrate, and His Soveraign Authority. This is undeniably irrefragable; for, in ſo far, as the Publike Intereſt is beyond the Private, in regard of worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence, and as to intemerable preſervation; ſo far is the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice done to the juſt right of the Soveraign Magiſtrate and His Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, incomparably ſinful, beyond what can be done to the right of any private Subject or Subjects whatſomever. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſ. 5ta.</hi> There is this fifth Propoſition. The juſt right of the Soveraign Magiſtrate and His Authority, is egregiouſly tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon and prejudged, when private Subjects encroach upon it, and do upon ſuſpition or jealouſie of diſallowed intentions or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Soveraign Princes, combine, confederate or binde themſelves to Allow, Enact, or Eſtabliſh any thing (much more, to reverſe or repeal allowed eſtabliſhed and ſtanding Laws) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any matters belonging to Religion, (upon the wele or ill adminiſtration whereof, the greateſt ſecurity or ruine of a State depends) without much more againſt the conſent and command of lawful Soveraign Authority. This Propoſition is clear, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Municipal and known Laws of this Kingdom, but even from the very Law and light of nature it ſelf; for it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to every Tenderer of Soveraignty, that it is one of the choiſeſt and moſt inviolable Jewels of the Crown of a Supream Power, to which none are co-ordinate, but all ſubordinate, as to every Supream Power, as Supream, all muſt needs be; <hi>viz.</hi> That no Popular Combinations, Bonds or Leagues, ſhould be among Subjects, upon what ſcore or pretence how ſpecious ſoever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, much leſſe againſt the conſent and command of the Authority <pb n="7" facs="tcp:135127:4"/> foreſaid; for, and if it were f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee for Subjects, thus at pleaſure to Combine, Confederate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A King (in which the Supream Power, in a true Monarchy, reſides) were but a bare, weak, titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar King, and ſhaddow only of a Soveraign, depending <hi>prècario</hi> upon the Subjects, whom at pleaſure they might caſt off or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; nay, and of it ſelf, it opens a patent door for the everſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ruine of all Government and Supream Power, ſo that any who will, may, by a Confederacy rebel, upon one pretext or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hence it's evident, there can be no greater encroachment upon, no higher prejudice done unto Soveraign Authority, then for Subjects in any-wiſe to Combine or Bind themſelves, againſt the Supream Royal Will and without conſent of the Soveraign. And, if it be, ſo high a prejudice done to the juſt right of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, for Subjects in any caſe to Combine or Confederat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, were it even to the carrying on of ſtanding and known Laws; what a heinous injury muſt it infer, upon the Soveraignes juſt right? for Subjects to Combine for the reverſing and repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of eſtabliſhed and ſtanding Laws, without, nay, and forcibly againſt Royal Commands: is not this, the moſt ſuperlative and tranſcendent prejudice, which can be done to the juſt right of the Supream Authority?</p>
            <p>But here now, that we may a little more unfold this Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it would be noticed that it is deem'd a favourable plea by ſome, for Subjects, tho in no caſe elſe, yet in the Concern of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to Combine and Confederate, without the allowance or conſent of Soveraign Authority, for redreſſing abuſes and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming diſorders therein; eſpecially when the Supream Magiſtrate being required thereto, doth deny his concurrence, and withhold the ſhoulder. But ſuch men, they are not aware, that in this they joyne iſſue with Phanatick <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and the bloodieſt of the Popes devotionaries (who with them, in this, reſemble <hi>Sampſon's</hi> Foxes, being linkt together by the Tails, though their Heads look different wayes) and with them cry up the lawfulneſſe of carrying on a Reformation in Religion, by outward force and violence: ſo much contrary to the wayes and Word of God, <hi>Joh. 18. 36. My Kingdom is not of this world,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If it were, my ſervants would fight.</hi> Where, bleſſed Chriſt Jeſus doth plainly inſinuate, that His Kingdom being ſpiritual, cannot, muſt not, be advanced with temporal armes: for the weapons of the Chriſtians warfare, are not <hi>Carnal,</hi> but <hi>Spiritual, 2 Cor.</hi> 10. 4. There is no command <pb n="8" facs="tcp:135127:5"/> from Chriſt to kill and ſlay the common enemies of our Religion, but contrariwiſe to pray for our perſecuters, and not to reſiſt evil,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 44. See alſo other Scriptures, ſuch as <hi>Zech. 4. 6. 1 Tim.</hi> 6. 2. and 2 <hi>Tim. 2. 25, &amp;c.</hi> Nay, and this courſe, it is againſt the very nature of Religion it ſelf; for, faith which is the Soul of Religion, is an inward act of the ſoul, which all the force in the world, can neither plant nor extirpate; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am ſuddenda non cogenda eſt.</hi> Conformable to this, was the conſtant Doctrine and Practice of the Pious, Sober, Primitive Church (which had learned better what belong'd to Authority, then to reſiſt the Ordinance of God, even in a Heathen <hi>Caeſar)</hi> whoſe Religion enjoyn'd them not to kill, but to be killed for it; Nor was this for want of ability but of Authority: As we read in the moſt Ancient Apologiſts for the Chriſtian Faith, ſuch as <hi>Arnob. Lactant. Cyprian: cont. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metr. Tertull. in apol. &amp;. ad Scap. Juſt. in Tryph. Auguſt. in Pſalm. 144. Ambroſ. in luc. 22. 38. Athan. epiſt. ad ſolit. vitam agentes, &amp;c.</hi> Then further, Popular Reformation, or Covenanting for Reformation of Religion without concurrence of the Supream Magiſtrate, hath no warrantable preſident, but rather to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in Sacred Writ: See thoſe Scriptures at convenience, <hi>Deut. 29. 2, 10, 11, 12, &amp;c. Joſh.
24. 25. 2 King. 23. 23. 2 Chron.</hi> 15. 8, 12. and <hi>cap.</hi> 29. 3, 10. and <hi>cap. 34. 31, 32. Ezra</hi> 10. 3, 4, 5. In all which and in many the like, you have ever the Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> &amp;c. concurring, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther going before the People, (as their place requir'd) in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Reformations therein mentionate; but no where the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Covenanting upon a Reformation of Religion (even in times of the worſt of Kings) without concurrence of the Supream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate:
<hi>Ariſe, for the matter belongs to thee</hi> (ſaith the whole Aſſembly of Elders there met) <hi>to Ezra, the prime Ruler;</hi> in that cited place, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10. 4. To ſhun the force of which Argument, and for a ſinful impairing the Supreme Power of the Soveraign; ſome have
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ancied a ſuppoſed co-ordination of power (I ſhall not once name theſe, whoſe impudence hath imboldned them to aſſert a monſtrous Subordination of the Soveraign to the People) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our King and His People in their repreſentative Meetings.</p>
            <p>This, indeed, is the Arch-pillar, upon which ſome of no ſmall Note, have laid the ſtreſſe of their Cauſe, for the ſupportment of the lawfulneſſe of Popular-reformings, without the Supreme and Royal Conſent. But, ſurely, this, as it is a moſt pernicious, ſo a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135127:5"/> moſt empty, airy, inconſequent ſpeculation. Inconſequent, becauſe, if a co-ordination of Soveraign Power, be ſuppoſed twixt King and People; then a joynt concurrence of both, in every act of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power, is neceſſary, if the act be not ſpurious and illegitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate: ſo that by this, the people, <hi>de jure,</hi> may no more reform without the King, then the King without the People; both ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered (according to this dream) being but <hi>Subjecta po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtat is ſupremae partial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and both joyntly conſidered only, the adaequat and complete ſubject of Soveraignty. Empty and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for, what a wilde imagination is it, to place a co-ordinate power with the King, in the repreſentative Body of the People, when the Soveraign only, hath by fundamental Law, the right of calling, and then of diſſolving, at pleaſure, the ſaid Body; and what an abſurd phoenomenon muſt it needs be? to conceive in a body, a co-ordination twixt the Members and the Head thereof; and the King is the Head of all the Tribes, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 17. and ſuch an Head, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſedes meri imperij eſt.</hi> But further, this whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey is repugnant to the true condition of Monarchy; for, this ſuppoſed co-ordination of the Supreme juſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive Power, muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily infer or ſuppoſe a communicability of the Soveraign Power, to more then one; which, notwithſtanding, in true Monarchy, is ſo properly belonging to, and ſo inſeparably ſetled in the Perſon of the Soveraign Prince, as that it cannot be derived or communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to any other, ſave only in way of deputation and commiſſion when and how far forth himſelf pleaſeth, in the outward exerciſe and adminiſtration of the ſame. Since as <hi>Bodin</hi> rightly giveth it; <hi>Neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt ut regnum quantumcunque eſt, ac jura omnia Majeſtatis, in ſolidum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NI, partitione ſublatâ, tribuantur; alioquin non Monarchia ſed Polyarchia dicetur. De republ. lib. 6. cap.</hi> 8. And indeed, however many Sharers there are in the Supreme Power, ſo many Supreme Governours or Soveraigns (reſpectively, and according to the different Intereſts they have, more or leſſe) there ſhall be. Oh, what Chimera's of invention, wil men make uſe of to uphold moſt groundleſſe conceits, they have once em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, for ſtrengthning and promoving of their ſinful and ſelfie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and intereſts. But to leave this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rpoſ.
6ta.</hi> There is this ſixth Propoſition. A juſtifiable Oath muſt be undertaken <hi>in bonum finem,</hi> for good ends and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; ends, conſiſtent with the welfare of our Neighbour, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Church and State we live in. (A clauſe, ſay Caſuiſts, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:135127:6"/> neceſſarily ſuppoſed, though not alwayes expreſſed in ſuch engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) under this, much is comprehended; as, that a lawfull Oath cannot engage to the doing of any thing, repugnant or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive, to the performance of ſome greater moral duty, one or another: ſo the Learned
<hi>Grotius, de jur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> belli, lib. 2. cap. 13. n. 7. Immo, etiam ſi res quae promittitur non ſit illicita, ſed majus bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num morale impediens; ſic quoque non valebit jurawentum,</hi> &amp;c. Hence alſo it it is, that we ought by no means, to Vow, Promiſe or Swear peremptorly, againſt the doing of any thing, which yet the real equity thereof, either then, or upon occaſion farely offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, may afterwards juſtly require and efflagitate at our hands. The ground of this comprehenſive Propoſition, briefly is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the greater moral duty, is ſtill to be preferred to the leſſer, as to practice and performance; and in affirmative precepts, this is acknowledg'dly evident; theſe being ſuch as oblige, <hi>licet ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, non tamen ad ſemper;</hi> as Divines univerſally take it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſ. 7ma.</hi> There is this ſeventh Propoſition. No Oath is or can be juſtifiable or of binding force, which is taken againſt a righteous, laudable Oath formerly ſworn. For, one lawful Oath can never make void another, much leſſe can an unlawful, vacat the obligation of a righteous Oath. It is a clear caſe reſolv'd by Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Caſuiſts, that a lawful Oath cannot be <hi>contra pactum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod licitum prius initum;</hi> for ſuch ſuper-faetation of diſſonant Oaths or Promiſes, doth ever beget a direct nullity in the latter. So that he who hath ſworn Allegiance to the Soveraign, and to maintain Epiſcopal Government in the Church; (which we now ſuppoſe to be lawful) and thereby bound himſelf, to maintain the juſt Right, Power and Authority of his ſaid Soveraign, or the forſaid Form of Church-Government, he cannot, by any ſecond or ſupervenient Oath, be tied, to do any thing that may tend to the violation or infringement of his former engagement; and if he have ſo inſnar'd himſelf, the obligation is, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> void and null. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſ. 8va, &amp; ult.</hi> There is this eight and laſt Propoſition. A man is bound in conſcience, to reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, renounce and diſclaim that, Which he was induced to engage himſelf by Oath, unlawfully to perform. For, an Oath, which is, <hi>Sacramentum pietatis,</hi> as it is in the mouths of all, cannot be
<hi>vinculum iniquit at is,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a bond of iniquity. No man can be, by any raſh Oath, or any Oath whatſomever, engaged ſo, as to ſtand oblidged, to do <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135127:6"/> and perform that, which is in it ſelf ſinful and unlawful to be done; but
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bound in couſcience to break that ſnare which was never a real, but meerly a ſuppoſed Bond.
<hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith well, <hi>2da, 2dae. quaeſt. 89. Jurans illicitum, peccat jurando, &amp; peccat ſervando.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Over and beyond all theſe, there are (I know) many other caſes, in which, the perſon once engaged to act, may be diſobliged from a neceſſary performance; as, when he pomiſes or ſwears, to perform ſomewhat impoſſible, and beyond his reach; <hi>De impoſſibilibus, enim, nemo tenetur,</hi> is the received maxime: or, when his condition is notably changed, from what it was, when firſt he entered the obligation; for then, ſome inevitable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe impediment, may obſtruct the performance: and many ſuch-like uſeful Caſes may be touch'd upon; but the Propoſitions already laid down, are the moſt Catholick or Univerſal and ſureſt Land-marks, by which, we may examine the legality and binding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of whatever engagements; where they fail All, or any of them, the ſuppoſed Promiſe or Oath, doubtleſſe, becomes void and fruſtrate; intangle us it may, in the Snares and Bonds of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, as the wiſe man calls them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5. 22. but not oblige us to a neceſſary performance of the thing undertaken; not even then, when as we freely and voluntarily incur the ſnare, much leſſe, when it is forced upon us (which is much to be adverted in our preſent diſquiry) by an over-awing, prevailing Faction; This looſens and weakens the ty much, if ſuperveening thus to other circumſtances; for, <hi>Non poteſt id civium conſenſu factum cenſeri, quod ereptâ libertate fiat. Bodin. de rep. lib. 2. c.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>And now, if our late Oaths, Covenants and Leagues, be ſquar'd according to theſe irrefragable rules above recorded; what bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingneſſe or obligation may be found in them, will be eaſie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine and reſolve, by their impingence upon moſt of the forſaid Propoſitions: All theſe popular and tumultuary engagements, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their very eſſence, combinations among factious Subjects, without and againſt the known will and conſent of Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and that, not to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y on or purſue laudbale and ſetled Laws, but (without all paralell) to reverſe and repeal eſtabliſhed and ſtanding Laws, againſt the Royal Will of our Soveraign Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver; and, therefore, in the judgement of the moſt rigid at this day, acknowledged to have had much ſin in them, upon this very Score. Much might be ſaid in diſcovery of the ſinfulneſſe and unlawfulneſſe of theſe late Covenants and Oaths; not only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <pb n="12" facs="tcp:135127:7"/> of their efficient Cauſe, as made by Subjects againſt the will of their Soveraign, in ſuch things as neceſſarily required His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: but further, in reſpect of their ſubject-matter, as being guilty of high injuſtice to the right of the King, both in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of combination without Him, and of conditional Allegiance to and preſervation of Him, as alſo, the altering of Religion eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law, without His conſent; and as engaging, to accuſe all Malignants (not accepting a mans own ſelf) and to endeavour that all ſuch, may be brought to puniſhment, without hope of mercy or pardon; binding alſo to pull down the eſtabliſhed Church-Government, before agreement upon another; and every man to go before another in the example of Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either waiting for the Miniſter to direct, or Magiſtrates Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to lead the way; then theſe, what can be more unjuſt? binding alſo to impoſſibilities; as, to defend and aſſiſt ALL that engage into theſe O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; and never to offer their opinions to neutrality or indifferency: the very taking alſo of theſe Oaths, was, <hi>in fact,</hi> directly contradicent to the formal words thereof; for, whereas they ſwear to extirpate Schiſm and Faction and to preſerve the Liberties of the Kingdomes and Authority of the King; The very taking and enforcing of theſe Oaths, being a vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Schiſm from their Mother-Church, a ſworn Faction againſt their more Loyal Neighbours, the greateſt prejudice to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdoms, the taking of theſe being deſtructive to all legal Publike Liberties; and the higheſt contempt that could be offered to the Kings Authority; as appeareth not only from what is above-ſaid, but further in this, that ſome of theſe Oaths did engage, abſolutely to preſerve the power of Parliaments, but the Kings Perſon and Authority with reſervation; for this end <hi>(forſooth)</hi> that the world may judge of their Loyalty, and how they had no intention to diminiſh his juſt Power. But left this ſhort word, by inlarging on theſe and ſuch like peccancies of theſe late Covenant-Oaths, ſhould ſwell into a volumne; We ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear: Nor ſhall we ſpeak of the unparalelled fraud and force, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in impoſing theſe Oaths, upon honeſt and wel-meaning Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; neither of the grand impoſtur's, whereby factious and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſigning men, did ſpeciouſly uſher-in and drive-on, their own baſe carnal intereſts, under the colour of the intereſts of Jeſus Chriſt, in our ſadly-experienced late Tragedies: And ſhal briefly, draw a corrolary, from theſe above-ſpecified Propoſitions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135127:7"/> the Point of Epiſcopal Government in this Church, and the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eming obligation of the Subjects in this Land, by their Oaths and Vows, againſt it. And it is this.
1. That theſe Oaths, in the firſt place, were, in the judgement of many of the moſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Learned, ſimply ſinful and unjuſt; upon the ſcore of their tendency to the extirpation of that form of Church-Government, which they conceived to be of Divine Right and Inſtitution; ſo that in order to all theſe, who were then, or are yet, of perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Epiſcopacyis, <hi>jure divino,</hi> theſe Oaths cannot be ſuppoſed to be any wiſe in point of conſcience binding: And, ſure, more may be ſaid, for a Divine Right and Inſtitution, of an imparity in degrees and even in office, among Church-guides, and ſo, for Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, then can be, for any other Form, or Model of Church-Government in the World. But, Secondly, Paſſing this, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing only Epiſcopal Government to have been, upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, indifferent; (as, I truſt, the more modeſt, ſober and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate will readily acknowledge) then, for Subjects to engage by Covenants or Oaths, for the utter extirpation thereof, without the concurrence of Supreme Authority, nay, and againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and expreſſe will of the Soveraign Magiſtrate, and the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed ſtanding Laws of this Kingdom, of which, the King alone is the Fountain and Origine; <hi>Cum ipſe ſit author juris, ut Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton. lib. 3. tra.</hi> 1. <hi>c. 9.</hi> And as another eminent in Law, ſaith wele, <hi>Vita &amp; caput &amp; autoritas in Principe eſt, omnium, quae in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica agi ſolent.</hi> How ſinful, then, muſt needs theſe Oaths and Engagements, have been? How contrary to the juſt Right of the Soveraign? (Who in <hi>Adiaphoris</hi> and indifferents, is acknowledg'd by all, to be <hi>Summus &amp; Supremus Arbiter)</hi> and therefore how invalid and inſufficient, as to obligation upon any, who have been inſnared by them; is obvious to every eye, that will not ſhut it ſelf, againſt convincing light: How much, alſo, ſuch are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heartily to homologat and cloſe with His Majeſti's Gracious Reſolutions, in the preſent ſetlement of this long toſſed Church; is as apparent. But, Thirdly, As to the moſt rigid, who (to the admiration of the truely Sober) would aſſert an intrinſecal unlawfulneſſe and ſinfulneſſe, in Epiſcopal Government, however ſo wel regulated; I ſay, that even their Oath for the Extirpation of Epiſcopal Government, cannot oblige even as to them; being that for private Subjects by themſelves, to endeavour to eſtabliſh or prefer any new Law, however ſo juſt and laudable in it ſelf, or <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135127:8"/> to reverſe and reſcind any ſtanding Law, however ſo unjuſt and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, againſt or without the Soveraign's Will and Royal conſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, is heinouſly ſinful and rebellious, and in it ſelf, and <hi>fine operis,</hi> plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Anarchical and everſive of all Government whatſomever: and, I truſt, no Oath to act rebellion, ſin or Anarchy, will be ſuppoſed by any ſober, to be binding, unleſſe it be to a ſpeedy and hearty repentance; ſo that even the Engagements and Oaths of thoſe who are moſt rigid in this matter, were in themſelves, beyond all contradiction, ſinful; and therefore can in no wayes be obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive even as to thoſe: So that, upon what ever account elſe it may be, that it pleaſeth ſome men zealouſly to engage againſt Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, in its preſent ſetlement and re-eſtabliſhment, it cannot be upon the value of their Oath (as they would make ſimple people to believe, as if that were an indiſpenſablety ſtreſſing their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences) that being in its own nature, ſinful (all combinations without Soveraign conſent, being ſuch, as themſelves will now freely acknowledge) and therefore they cannot but ſee themſelves in conſcience obliged to reverſe and mourn for theſe their ſinful Oaths. And to deal a little freely, ſo much talking of Oaths, and indiſpenſable Oaths, with the frequent threats of the danger of perjury, which have been ſo much thundred out, to fright wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning and tender Chriſtians; cannot be look'd upon by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering perſons, but as ſo many methods and impoſtures to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude: whileas, even the moſt violent preſſers of the bindingneſſe of theſe Oaths againſt Epiſcopacy, do in their open profeſſions and acknowledgements, renounce and diſclaim the obligations of theſe Oaths, as to the combination and confederacy that is in them (conſederacies and combinations among Subjects, upon what pretext ſoever, without ſpecial allowance and conſent of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate, being, by themſelves acknowledged to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and rebellious) which yet is, if not, the very <hi>formalis ratio</hi> and eſſence of theſe enſnaring Covenant-Oaths, yet doubtleſſe, the prime object and man foundation of them: whileas alſo they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the unbindingneſſe of theſe ſame Oaths, as to conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and reſerv'd Allegiance, by undue and unwarrantable limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and reſtrictions; and yet ſtill preſſe the Oath and its bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſſe againſt Epiſcopal Government: and in a copulative Oath (ſuch as theſe Oaths and Covenants acknowledge themſelves to be) if the obligation, as to any one point, be diſſolved and looſed, it can hardly be underſtood, how as to the whole or any other <pb n="15" facs="tcp:135127:8"/> particular, there can be any more bindingneſſe therein. What will the forſaid acknowledgments infer, being weighed in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of diſcerning men, but that, were it not, that the fear of incurring the cenſure and penalties of treaſon, did overawe; theſe Covenant-Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would be ſtill vigorouſly aſſerted, to be as binding and obligative in point of combination, without and againſt the Soveraign Magiſtrate's conſent; and in order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional and limited Allegiance, as they are ſaid to be, in order to the point of Epiſcopacy. To diſpenſe with theſe Oaths and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-engagements in theſe great Points and Intereſts, and yet, ſtill to ſet out the ſame as indiſpenſable tyes and Sacred inviolable Bonds, againſt Epiſcopal-Government; is not this handſomely to play the Pope? in diſpenſing in ſome more weighty, and binding conſciences, in lighter concerns of one and the ſame copulative Oath: or is it not rather (as ſome obſerving perſons, give it) to act the impoſtures, in impoſing upon the Peoples eaſineſſe and credulity, for upholding of the tottering
<hi>Diana</hi> of a Para-mount Power, ſome have ſo ſinfully uſurped, and ſo tyrannically practiſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and are yet ſo unwilling to part with, left the power of this Church be recovered into thoſe hands, out of which it was wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by violence and injuſtice.</p>
            <p>And what a needleſſe noiſe is it, that is ſo much raiſed by the zealous clamors of ſome, againſt Epiſcopacy; may it not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered, that it was declared, by the contrivers and abettors of the Covenant, in its firſt riſe; that though they ſuppoſed Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy to be againſt Law in <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet, they did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any, by taking of the Covenant to abjure it, but that the practiſe of it ſhould be forborn and the matter referred to a free General Aſſembly. <hi>See Miniſters Anſw. to the 4. dem. of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of Aberdene.</hi> And one would think that the edge of ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous zeal, might have been rather blunted then ſharpned, by theſe laſt three and twenty years exeperience. And is not Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy a Government, which had its riſe in the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and by continual and univerſal ſucceſſion; hath ſince, been ſtill owned and practiſed by the Chriſtian Church; as the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſucceſſion of Biſhops in the See's of
<hi>Alexandria,</hi> from <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt; in
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle; in <hi>Antioch</hi> from <hi>Peter</hi> &amp;c. ſhew, If hiſtorical credit may be given to ſuch Worthies, as <hi>Irenaeus, Euſebius, Socrates, Theodoret, Hierom,</hi> with many other grave and famous Eccleſiaſtick Writers; in ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135127:9"/> much, that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tus, for affirming a Biſhop not to be above a ſingle Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, was generally reputed by the Chriſtian World for thirteen hundred years together, as well in the Eaſtern as Weſtern Church, for a down-right Heretick: a Government which hath been ſtill owned in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when Order and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment did overtop Faction and Intereſt, and ever ſtill, till Seditions, Tumults, Inſurrections and Rebellions did go current for Diſcipline and Order: And in a word, a Government, which by the univerſal conſent of the Churches of Chriſtendome, both in <hi>Aſia, Africk, Grece, Ruſſia,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> that never acknowledged any ſubjection to, or dependance upon the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath been conſtantly embraced, and the Opugners of it generally branded for Hereticks; which of all other Forms hath undovbted the beſt Title to Divine or Apoſtolical Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; againſt which nothing is, or ever could be, objected, but the humane infirmities and perſonal failings of ſome particular men, from which no Government is or can be totally exempted and priviledged; which, in the moſt of theſe few Churches who want it (ſome whereof are under the want of Biſhops, becauſe they cannot tell how to come by them, their Princes being of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Religion, and ſo will allow none but of their own; others there be, who are willingly without them, becauſe ſetled in ſuch a Government, as they find moſt ſuitable to a Popular State, and dare not venture upon a change; all others enjoying the felicity of Epiſcopal Government, either the thing and name both, or elſe the thing under another name, <hi>viz.</hi> Superintendents, Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by their beſt and ableſt Miniſters, hath been fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deſired. Our practiſe, ſure, is without all parallel, in that never did we read of any Church, before a miſleading Faction in this our Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that ever turn'd out their Biſhops (if they were of the ſame Religion) vowing to root them out by the Sword, contrary to the command of the Supream Lawful Magiſtrate. So that we muſt needs accuſe all the World beſides our ſelves, of folly, Antichriſtianiſm and ignorance, or then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to forbear our peeviſh quarrellings againſt this Government of the Church by Biſhops, to which through Gods Mercy, and His Majeſties care, this broken Church is again reſtored. To all the former it may be added, that in all the Bible it is not to be ſound, that the power either of Ordination of Juriſdiction, ever was exerciſed by a ſingl. Presbytery (yea, and it is none of the <pb n="17" facs="tcp:135127:9"/> leaſt of doubts, whether there be mention of any judicial conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of ſingle Presbyters <hi>ſimpliciter pares,</hi> in all Sacred Writ) without delegation from, and in a dependence upon a Superiour Power, reſiding in a ſingle perſon. If then, the deſign of ſome Zelots againſt Epiſcopacy, may not ſeem to have worſe at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and do not tend to lead Subjects into miſconſtructions of His Majeſties Gracious Intentions, let the impartial, determine. So that, to draw towards a concluſion, we may ſee, how contrary ſuch Oaths and Vows are to the duty which good Subjects, by vertue of their relation, and as Subjects, they owe to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; how contrary to due Allegiance; how obſtructive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant, to the performance, of the great moral duty of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, due by Subjects to Supreme Authority, and the eſtabliſhed Laws thereof; as alſo, how inconſiſtent with the welfare of the Church, and State we live in; and conſequently how ſinful, is eaſie to diſcern by comparing theſe Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the irrefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable Propoſitions, above ſet down.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if any (according to our laſt Propoſition) good Subject or Subjects, have been drawn, by any pretence, perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or force whatſomever to bind himſelf by Oath or Covenant againſt Epiſcopal Government, which was, and now again is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law; he hath not ſworn in juſtice, but engag'd himſelf to the certain prejudice of His Soveraign's juſt Right, by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful combining with private Subjects againſt His Authority, to the doing of many things contrary to eſtabliſhed Law, and (which is moſt impious) by endeavouring to introduce the form of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath upon a matter ſo incapable of, and indiſpoſed for ſuch a Form; if any, I ſay, hath been thus engag'd, he is obliged, in duty and conſcience to diſclaim, reverſe and renounce his ſaid act; otherwiſe, beſide the horrid ſcandal which he ſhall draw upon the Reformed Religion, he doth run himſelf upon the breach of the third Command, by making his Oath, a bond of iniquity. And for the further ſatiſfaction, of the ſatisfiable; it may ponderate, that the power impoſing theſe Oaths, was originally invalid and naught; and where the fountain is corrupt, the ſtreams iſſuing thence, can by no means run clear, <hi>Nam quod deeſt in cauſa deeſt in effectu;</hi> and therefore, what is done in vertue of ſuch invalid power, can ſcarce amount to right or lawful; as grounded upon ſuch a rotten <hi>Baſis</hi> of pretended Authority. And, which ought exceedingly to ſtisfie Subjects, in their diſ-obligation from theſe <pb n="18" facs="tcp:135127:10"/> enſnaring tyes, Our Father, I mean, <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> without whoſe conſent, no vow or engagement of the childe is obligative, as we may ſee, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. 4, 5, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> that a Virgin or a Wiſe making a vow without conſent of the Father or Husband, is diſ-obliged therefrom, if the Husband or Father hearing of the vow, do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow thereof; and, we being, in a moral ſenſe, as much at the diſpoſe of the King, the Father of the Countrey, the Civil Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all, if not more then Children at the diſpoſe of their natural Parents, whileas the vows forſaid are diſpenc'd and irritate by Him, they can be no more binding tyes to us, (ſuppoſe them otherwiſe lawful) and we, His diffent being any wayes ſignified to us, are diſ-oblig'd and no more bound, but may forgo theſe vows; and in our ſo doing, the Lord will forgive us, as it is in <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. 6. forgive us, not for that we renounce theſe Vows, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duty; but for our raſh or cowardiſh engagement in them, without due conſent, that being our ſin.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that, our Civil Father, His Majeſty His conſent was indulg'd to theſe Engagements, which may therefore be ſtill ſuppoſ'd to be binding, To this it is replied. Firſt, This doth not take away the unlawfulneſſe of any of theſe Oaths and Vows, which were undertaken, antecedently to any Royal and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative conſent thereto procured; ſo that ſuch who before that before-alleg'd conſent, did engage in theſe combinatory Oaths, did therein heinouſly ſin, ſo that theſe are thereby oblig'd to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Repentance; The firſt Swearing and Covenanting at leaſt, being rebellious and ſinful. But, Secondly, Any Royal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that ever was procured or granted, was a violented, coacted conſent, and therefore, in Law, to be look't upon by all honeſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as a non-conſent, <hi>coactus enim conſenſus, nullus;</hi> ſo that the Princes involuntary and conſtrained yeelding and ceding to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Faction, affords and layes no juſt title or ground of obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no not upon Himſelf, in the exteriour Court, much leſſe upon His Subjects:
<hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, ex actione involuntaria, non naſcitur, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatio. reg. juris. vid. cod. hb. 2. tit.
20.</hi> And then, Thirdly, That ſuppoſed conſent of our preſent Soveraign, is obvious to the eye of all the World, to have been forc'd and coacted; He being by a Faction in this Kingdome, at that time, moſt unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and diſloyally kept, as a Noble Priſoner, rather then a free King, and by them violented, to give colour of life to theſe things, which in their very nature did bereave Soveraignty of its <pb n="19" facs="tcp:135127:10"/> breath: and therefore that conſent is now repeal'd, as appeareth from His Majeſties preſent Reſolutions, and His High and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Council, their Proclamation, of the date <hi>September,</hi> 1661. relating to Church-Government. So that hence no ſhew of any title of obligation, as to theſe Vows and Oaths, doth affect the Subjects, but rather to the contrary; His diffent being of equal force to diſoblige, as His conſent is, to ty or oblige.</p>
            <p>And now, by this time, I truſt, it doth appear, that for any ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to oppoſe the ſetlement of this Church by Epiſcopacy, is ſo unwarrantable; that none who hath any ſenſe of Religion to God, of charity to their Mother-Church, or of grateful duty to their Gracious King, will preſume to juſtifie; and, if any will prove ſo peeviſh; Subjects, I truſt, know better how to value Peace, being ſo harraſſed and ſpoil'd by the late inteſtine Diviſions, then to be ſo eaſily engag'd again, to devote that little blood and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which remains, to the ſinful and ambitious luſts of a few men whom, though our King and this Kingdom were not able to call to an account, (which yet they may find) yet there is a God in heaven, who ſeeth all their hearts, and will one day, judge and be aveng'd of all ſuch their ſinful actions.</p>
            <p>By what is ſaid, men may ſee, at any time, how weak the cords of an unlawful Oath, Vow, or Engagement are and how little they bind, ſave only to Repentance, and that for their unadviſed raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if ſpontaneouſly undertaken, and for their cowardiſe, if through fear, ſubmitted to. By this alſo it may appear to how little purpoſe, men make uſe of theſe tyes and fetters, that bind not in truth, but only enſnare; like to thoſe cords where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Sampſon</hi> was bound, and as eaſily upon occaſion broken aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; being, that there wants a twiſting-in of theſe conditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Propoſitions premiſed, to ſtrengthen and confirm them: nay, ſo far are they, from holding faſt the perſon Engaged, that upon a due back-ſearch and examination, they help to ſet him looſer; when as he ſhall ſeriouſly bethink himſelf of the guilt and burden of ſin he yet lyes under; <hi>Nam tolerabilius eſt promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum non facere quod turpe, eſt. Ambroſ. de offic. lib. 3. cap.</hi> 12. no other way of eſcape, then, but by a ſpeedy cancelling of the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
            <p>Briefly, and to conclude this ſhort word, for ſatisfaction (in which we have appeared, upon no other incentives, but, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, of Loyalty, and of zeal for order and beauty, in this our <pb n="20" facs="tcp:135127:11"/> Mother-Church) of the Scrupulous; Where the Promiſe or Oath, both for matter and manner, is rightly undertaken; we cannot be too anxious and ſolicitons in keeping of it, ſo <hi>Matth. 5. 33. Religioſe obſerva juramentum:</hi> was one of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> his firſt leſſons to his Diſciples; yea, God himſelf, hath vouchſaſed it a room, within the catalogue of his moſt glorious titles, of being faithful, and keeping Covenant: otherwiſe, where fraud or force, with the like, ſhall happen to interpoſe, and withall, the matter, in many reſpects above-ſpecified, be injuſtifiable; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch an obligation, when, or whereſoever undertaken; the beſt reſolution, in my humble opinion, is, that it is ill taken and worſe kept; nay, and is of it ſelf void from the beginning, and binds to nothing, but, what I heartily wiſh, all may find in the end, <hi>REPENTANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="judgment">
            <p>
               <hi>Si quis neceſſitate coactus juraverit, pignuſve poſuerit, quo is ad inſidias Domino ſuo parandas, vel
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pem, injuſte cuivis feren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, adſtringitur, reſiliat potius quam quo coepit, inſiſtat, ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus. L L. Alured. c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſilium, prudenſque animi ſententia jurat, Et niſi judicii, vincula nulla tenent.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135127:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
